A Finding Aid to the Alson Skinner Clark Papers, 1870-1971, bulk 1890-1940, in the Archives of American Art AAA.claralso
Archives of American Art
Alson Skinner Clark papers
bulk 1890-1940
1870-1971
AAA.claralso
Archives of American Art
7.2 Linear feet
The papers of painter and muralist Alson Skinner Clark measure 7.2 linear feet and date from 1870 to 1971, with the bulk of the material from 1890 to 1940. Clark's career is documented through biographical material; correspondence with family, friends, galleries, and dealers; eleven diaries by the artist as well as 16 by his wife Medora Clark; stories and essays by Medora; financial records and business files of art and civilian concerns; assorted printed material including exhibition catalogs and announcements, maps, news clippings (singly and in scrapbooks), advertisements, and ephemera; and photographs of the artist, his friends and family, studio, travels, and artwork.
Clark, Alson Skinner, 1876-1949
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 9 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1890-1958 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1895-1962 (Boxes 1-2; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Diaries, 1889-1922 (Boxes 2-4; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1900-1962 (Boxes 4-5; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, 1889-1930 (Boxes 5, 8; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1890-1971 (Boxes 5-6; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1910-1920 (Box 6; 2 folders)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1885-1935 (Boxes 6, 8, 9; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 9: Scrapbooks, 1902-1955 (Boxes 7, 8; 0.5 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Alson Skinner Clark (1876-1949) was a painter and muralist who travelled and worked in Europe, Mexico, Canada, Panama, and the United States, ultimately settling in southern California.
Clark was born in Chicago, Illinois, and began training in 1891 at the age of 11 at the Art Institute of Chicago. In 1896 he studied under William Merritt Chase at the Art Students’ League of New York and briefly at the Chase School of Art before moving to Paris to train with James Abbott McNeill Whistler at the Academia Carmen in 1898. Alongside his wife, Medora (married 1902), Clark travelled extensively, painting the landscapes and urban activity of Chicago, New York, Quebec, France, Dalmatia, and Spain.
In 1913, Clark journeyed to Panama to document the construction of the canal, and in 1919, after serving as a military photographer in World War I, he settled in Pasadena, California, where he adopted the landscapes and colonial architecture of Mexico and the American West as subjects en plein air. It was during this time that Clark began to take on work as a muralist, accepting commissions from the local bank and theatre while also embarking on a teaching career at Occidental College and eventually the Stickney Memorial School of Fine Arts, where he served as director.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Glass plate negatives are closed to researchers. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The 1897 diary, sales notebook, glass negatives, and albums of negatives were donated in 1986 by Joseph Moure, an art historian who purchased the material from occupants of Clark's former studio. The remainder was donated by Clark's son, Alson Clark, in 1989, 1991, 1992, and 1997 and by Clark's grandniece, Deborah Clark, in 2006.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and muralist Alson Skinner Clark measure 7.2 linear feet and date from 1870 to 1971, with the bulk of the material from 1890 to 1940. Clark's career is documented through biographical material; correspondence with family, friends, galleries, and dealers; eleven diaries by the artist as well as 16 by his wife Medora Clark; stories and essays by Medora; financial records and business files of art and civilian concerns; assorted printed material including exhibition catalogs and announcements, maps, news clippings (singly and in scrapbooks), advertisements, and ephemera; and photographs of the artist, his friends and family, studio, travels, and artwork.
Clark, Medora; Artists' studios--Photographs; Diaries; Glass negatives; Landscape painting; Mural painting and decoration, American; Painters--California; Painting, American; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Biographical Material, circa 1890-1958; Series 1; 6 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains scattered biographical documents. Found here are legal documents of citizenship, driving, and parking papers; miscellaneous biographical material, including a recipe, address list, and Chicago social organization roster; documents from Medora Clark’s membership in a Pasadena society club; and the typewritten and annotated transcript in two drafts of Margaret Truax Hunter’s oral history interview with Medora Clark in 1956.
  - Legal Papers, 1913-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Town Club Membership Material, Medora Clark, 1925-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transcript of Oral History Interview with Medora Clark, Part 1, 2nd Draft, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Transcript of Oral History Interview with Medora Clark, Part 2, 1st Draft, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Transcript of Oral History Interview with Medora Clark, Part 2, 2nd Draft, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1895-1962; Series 2; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence includes mostly personal exchanges with family and friends, but professional communications with galleries and dealers are also interspersed. Correspondence between Clark and his wife Medora constitute a large share of the series, with a significant body of letters from Clark’s time as a military photographer in World War I (1917-1919).
  Family correspondence is primarily with the artist’s mother Sarah Clark during the artist’s travels abroad and after settling in California in 1919. The artist’s brothers, Mancel Talcott Clark and Edwin Hill Clark, are also represented. Fellow artist and good friend Rufus Dreyer appears in correspondence from Paris in 1917.
  Correspondence with Amelia (Mela) Baker, a family friend since childhood, includes letters (sometimes illustrated) and postcards from Clark, his brothers, his mother, and Medora from 1895 to 1910.
  - Correspondence with Amelia Baker, 1895-1910 (Box 1, Folder 7-31)
  - General Correspondence, undated, circa 1895-1950 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
  - General Correspondence, 1870-1915 (Box 1, Folder 34-39)
  - General Correspondence, 1916-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-21)
  - Miscellaneous Envelopes, 1897-1916 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Diaries, 1889-1922; Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  This series contains 11 diaries belonging to Alson Skinner Clark and 16 belonging to his wife Medora. Of interest are Clark’s diaries from his first tour of Europe as a 13-year-old (1889); accounts of activities in the Art Students’ League and the Chase School of Art (1897 and 1898); and entries from his time as a military photographer (1918). Medora’s travel diaries include anecdotes and descriptions of the people and places the couple visited on their European travels (circa 1904-1909).
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  3.1: Diaries of Alson Skinner Clark
  3.2: Diaries of Medora Clark
  - Diaries of Alson Skinner Clark, 1889-1922; 3.1
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, May-July 1889 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, July-November 1889 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, November 1917-January 1918 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Diary of Alson Skinner Clark, 1919-1922 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Diaries of Medora Clark, 1891-1915; 3.2
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1891-1892 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Diary of Medora Clark, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Travel Diary of Dalmatia and Venice, circa 1904 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Travel Diary of Malaga and Grenada, circa 1909 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Travel Diary of Spain, circa 1909 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Writings, circa 1900-1962; Series 4; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  Writings are by Medora Clark and include notes and notebooks of drafts and story ideas as well as typewritten fiction short stories, nonfiction essays, and poems that she submitted to magazines for publication. Of interest are Medora’s accounts of her visit with Clark to the Panama Canal and her ruminations on art and art viewing.
  - Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notebook, circa 1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notebook, "Art, My Wiggly Tooth, M. Seguin's Goat", undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Notebook, "The Buying Public", undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Notebook, "London in Seven Days", undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, "Samplers, Canadian Story, Rochefort", circa 1902-1910 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Notebook, "Shipboard Story, en route to Tropics", circa 1913 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Notes, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Fiction, "After-Glow", circa 1921 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Fiction, "Aftermath of a Drought", circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Fiction, "Un Aperitif", circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Fiction, "A Bit of Desiccated Cloisonne", undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Fiction, "A Breton Mutiny", circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Fiction, "Casarabonela", undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Fiction, "A Chevrolet Flying", undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Fiction, "Connecticut", undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Fiction, "Consequences", undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Fiction, "The Court of LeRay de Chaumont", undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Fiction, "A Day of Court Life in Paris", undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Fiction, "The Drums", circa 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Fiction, "The Fields of Pemzec", circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Fiction, "The Green Bottle", circa 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Fiction, "The Happiness Kit", undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Fiction, "The Highway" (Three Versions), undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Fiction, "The Highway" Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Fiction, "The Highway" Working Drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 35-37)
  - Fiction, "Jack's Ghost Story", circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Fiction, "The Lion in Captivity", circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Fiction, "Milady's Retainer" (Incomplete), circa 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Fiction, "The Moment," Acts I, II, and III, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Fiction, "The Moment," Act I (Two Versions), undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Fiction, "The Moment," Act II, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Fiction, "The Moment," Act III (Two Versions), undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Fiction, "The Pasterijica", undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Fiction, "Peacock and Almonds", circa 1905-1915 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Fiction, "People" (Two Versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fiction, "The Release of the Lizards", circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fiction, "Reproaches to a Work-Table", circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Fiction, "A Successful Experiment", undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fiction, "Sunspots", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Fiction, "Torbas" (Three Versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Fiction, "Tumorius", circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fiction, "Two Afternoons in the Woods", circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Fiction, "Two Irish Anecdotes", circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Fiction, "Two Legends of Trecessions" (Two Versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Fiction, "Within the Gates" (Three Versions), circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Fiction, "The Yellow Helmet", undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Nonfiction, "Breton Life", circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Nonfiction, "Breton Slide Lecture", circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Nonfiction, "Defense Against Disaster", undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Nonfiction, "Early Settlers of Jefferson County, New York", undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Nonfiction, "The Fourth in Brittany", circa 1905 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Nonfiction, "French Art" (Incomplete), circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Nonfiction, "How to Look at Pictures", undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Nonfiction, "Letter to Century Magazine Regarding 'Our Barbarous Fourth'", 1908 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Nonfiction, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Nonfiction, "A Painter in Panama", 1913 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Nonfiction, "The Real Bohemia", undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Nonfiction, "Smells", undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Nonfiction, Untitled Essay, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Nonfiction, "The Zone from A Woman's Point of View" (Two Versions), circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Poems, circa 1908-1962 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Personal Business Records, 1889-1930; Series 5; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 5, 8
  This series contains financial and occupational documents related to art materials, memberships, sales, and shipping, as well as non-art transactions, such as hotel and restaurant receipts, home and car purchases, and invoices for leisure and material goods. Mailing lists include museums as well as private buyers.
  Inventories of artwork, including sales records and exhibition submissions, are represented in a card file inventory, notebooks, and a sales list. These inventories furnish information on the title, size, date, canvas, place of origin, varnish, exhibition history, and buyer (when applicable). Additionally, the sales notebook and sales list include small black and white photographs of artworks.
  - Bills and Receipts, Art Related, 1914-1928 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Bills and Receipts, Non-Art Related, 1907-1927 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Card File Inventory of Clark's Paintings, circa 1903-1911; (shoebox) (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Hotel and Restaurant Receipts, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Mailing Lists, circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Sales Notebook, circa 1915-1930 (Box 5, Folder 33-35)
  - Submission Notebook, 1905-1914 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Oversized Sales List with Images, circa 1915 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1890-1971; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  This series contains a Victoria and Albert Museum Accession Catalog from 1913; a Popular Monthly article on photography by Lawrence Fletcher, Ph.D.; exhibition announcements and catalogs; two pre-World War I maps of France and Brussels; arts and civil membership and association materials; miscellaneous ephemera, including a theatre program and tickets, ration notes, art material advertisements, and a Grand Canyon tour brochure; news clippings on the arts and Clark; and unmarked postcards of European landmarks and American laborers.
  - Accession Catalog, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Article, "A Talk About Photography", 1890 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1920-1930 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1915-1971 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Maps, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Memberships and Associations, 1915-1946 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1912-1957 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - News Clippings, circa 1909-1937 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Artwork, circa 1910-1920; Series 7; 2 Folders Box 6
  Artwork includes two pencil landscape drawings, labeled “Conquest of California by Sloat at Monterey” and “Gold Discovery;” one colored pencil figure drawing; and two small watercolor figure sketches, labeled “Uncle ‘Al’” and “Madam’s Assistant.” Also found here is a pen and ink diagram of the Panama Canal.
  - Pencil and Watercolor Studies, circa 1910-1920 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Profile of Panama Canal, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Photographs, circa 1885-1935; Series 8; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 6, 8, 9
  Found here are personal photographs of the artist, his friends and family, his Pasadena home and Palm Springs studio circa 1930, and his travels in Mexico and the American West. There is also a set of five cabinet cards of theatre portraits and the Treasure Island set that Clark designed for the Pasadena Playhouse. Photographs of artwork consist mostly of Clark’s paintings but also include reproduced engravings of California circa 1850 (filed in Photographs of Artwork, The West) and Alfred Maurer’s portraits.
  Negatives from the artist’s personal albums contain mostly travel images of Rochefort (circa 1907), Quebec/New York (circa 1908), and the American West (circa 1919), and are accompanied by indices. Glass plate negatives, which are housed separately and closed to researchers, document the artist’s family, artwork, and Southern California landscapes. These images can be seen in the contact sheets enclosed in this series. Oversized photographs include eight “California Club” portrait paintings, two images of a mural for Polytechnic Elementary School in Pasadena, and one photograph of a screen painted for Dalzell Wilson’s home in Pasadena.
  - Alson Skinner Clark, circa 1915-1918 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Friends and Family, circa 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Home and Studio, circa 1930 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Theatre Cabinet Cards, circa 1885-1900 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Travel, circa 1915-1930 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Treasure Island Set Design, circa 1926 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Alfred Maurer, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork, California, 1920s (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Chicago, Quebec, New York, 1904-1906 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Circle Theatre, circa 1926 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Artwork, European Paintings, 1904-1912 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Figure Paintings and Still Lifes, 1904-1934 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Landscape Paintings, circa 1910-1925 (Box 6, Folder 17-20)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Mexico, circa 1920-1935 (Box 6, Folder 21-25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Miscellaneous, 1900s-1920s (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Panama, circa 1913 (Box 6, Folder 27-28)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Pasadena First Trust and Savings Bank, 1928-1929 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Spain, 1909-1910 (Box 6, Folder 30-31)
  - Photographs of Artwork, The West, circa 1920-1930 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Film Negatives, Album A (Rochefort), circa 1907 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Film Negatives, Album B (Quebec), circa 1908 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Film Negatives, Album C (The West), 1919 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Film Negatives, Album Indices, circa 1907-1919 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Film Negatives, Miscellaneous, circa 1910-1935 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Contact Sheets of Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920-1930 (Box 6, Folder 38-39)
  - Oversized Photographs of Artwork, circa 1920-1933 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920-1930 (Box 9)
    see copy prints in Box 6, Folders 38-39
- Scrapbooks, 1902-1955; Series 9; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 7, 8
  This series contains three news clipping scrapbooks of articles and images documenting Clark and his work. Pieces of correspondence, exhibition literature, and miscellaneous ephemera are interspersed.
  - Scrapbook, 1909-1925 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbook, 1923-1955 (Box 7, Folder 5-9)
  - Oversized Scrapbook, 1902-1913 (Box 8, Folder 3)